The next section in your text deals with appendix, and this is a relatively short section,
so we're going to actually do two sections in this video, both appendix and then inflammatory bowel disease.
So the appendix, the only major thing to be aware of is something called acute appendicitis.
Obviously, this is acute inflammation of the appendiceal wall.
This is the most common cause of acute abdomen.
Acute abdomen is when a patient presents with severe abdominal pain, which is often a surgical emergency.
This is related to obstruction of the appendix by lymphoid hyperplasia or a fecalist.
So the idea here is that if you've got the appendix, the way by which the appendix gets inflamed is that you've got to block it with something.
And once you block it with something, then remember the general principle of pathology that when you create this block,
then basically behind the block you're going to get inflammation.
And so when there's a block, you're then going to get inflammation, in particular here, acute inflammation of the appendiceal wall,
which is, again, called appendicitis or acute appendicitis.
So this is what I say here in the text, and what I mean when I say that you've got to block it either with lymphoid hyperplasia.
So there's a ton of lymphoid tissue in the appendix.
If you go back to your normal histology, remember that you've got a lot of lymphoid tissue within the appendix,
and so you can get lymphoid hyperplasia if the child, for example, has some sort of gastrointestinal infection,
which could then result in appendicitis because it would block the lumen, or a fecalist,
which is basically just a piece of fecal material that would be a cause in adults.
Patients with acute appendicitis, they present with periumbilical pain, fever, and nausea.
These are very kind of classic signs and symptoms.
The pain initially is periumbilical, but eventually localizes to the right lower quadrant.
Rupture of the appendix could result in peritonitis, where you would inflame the peritoneum,
and that would present with guarding and rebound tenderness.
Now, guarding refers to the fact that there's so much pain in the abdomen that the patients keep themselves very tight,
and when you press down on the abdomen, you can feel the muscles sort of very tight,
trying to guard against you pressing any deeper.
And then rebound tenderness is when you press down on the abdominal wall and then let go.
It hurts a tremendous amount when you let go.
That's called rebound tenderness.
And, of course, you can develop an abscess around the appendix.
It's a common complication.
That would be called a periappendiceal abscess.
Moving right along to inflammatory bowel disease, this is a chronic relapsing inflammation of the bowel.
We don't know what causes it.
It could possibly be due to an abnormal immune response to enteric flora.
Classically, the presentation is that you get a patient who has recurrent bouts of bloody diarrhea and abdominal pain,
and this recurrent is important, as you'll see.
Usually it's, or more often, it's a young woman, classically in her teens to 30s,
but it can occur later in life, and, of course, males can be afflicted as well.
Now, this is more prevalent in the West, particularly in Caucasians and those of Eastern European Jewish descent.
It's a diagnosis of exclusion, and that's because when you have a patient who's got bloody diarrhea and abdominal pain,
there are a lot of things that would be up on the top of your differential before you would think about inflammatory bowel disease.
For example, infectious causes.
For example, ischemic causes.
And so, really, you've got to exclude a bunch of things before you can raise inflammatory bowel disease up on your differential diagnosis.
Now, there's two types of inflammatory bowel disease, or at least two major types, ulcerative colitis and Crohn's disease,
and it's very important to be familiar with each of these and the distinctions between them.
And so, we're going to walk you through this chart for the sake of making sure that you really understand these two disorders.
So, the first disorder is called ulcerative colitis, and the name tells you a lot.
Once you hear the word ulcerative, you know that the extent of the wall that's going to be involved is going to be predominantly mucosal with some mucosal ulceration.
Remember that the word ulcer basically means that you're damaging the mucosa and a little bit of the submucosa.
And so, I think that's easy, given the name.
As far as the location is concerned, this is going to involve the colon, hence the term colitis.
But what's important to note is that it always starts in the rectum, and then it works its way up the colon.
And as it works its way up the colon, it can extend to any level within the colon.
So, it could involve the rectum only, or it could move up and involve the rectum and the sigmoid,
or it could move up and involve the rectum, sigmoid, and the descending colon, etc.
And so, it'll go up the colon and then sort of stop.
And it can stop anywhere along the colon, but the most proximal that it can go,
as it goes backwards from the rectum up, the most proximal that it can go is the cecum.
So, the cecum is sort of the end point, and of course, that's the end point of the colon.
So, this disease can only involve the colon.
Remember also that when it starts in the rectum, it'll involve the entire radius of the tube.
So, it basically just sort of involves the complete surface of the tube wherever it's present,
and will work its way backward to a certain point.
The remainder of the GI tract, from the terminal ileum all the way up, is unaffected.
So, it's really restricted to the colon.
Now, because it's restricted to the colon, and particularly the rectum,
you're going to have left lower quadrant pain.
The left lower quadrant is where the rectum is located,
and of course, these patients are going to have bloody diarrhea.
Now, when you ask yourself, what is the key histologic hallmark of ulcerative colitis,
the answer is that it is a crypt abscess.
So, what is a crypt abscess?
Well, let's go back and remind ourselves of the normal histology.
When you look at the colon, it's a bunch of these sort of test tubes lined up.
That's the way the colon normally looks.
Each of these is called a crypt.
And so, the key histologic hallmark of ulcerative colitis is that you're going to get neutrophils within these crypts.
So, that's called a crypt abscess.
Now, you can see the crypt going up and down as a test tube,
or if you cut the test tube in cross-section, you would see the crypt looking like this.
Of course, these are the epithelial cells, and then it would be loaded with neutrophils in here.
And so, that is a crypt abscess, and that is the histologic hallmark of ulcerative colitis.
And you do need to be familiar with that.
The histologic hallmark is a crypt abscess.
And I'm going to show you some pictures at the very end of this discussion.
Now, what's the gross appearance?
Well, when you look at the colon grossly, you're going to see pseudopolyps.
And pseudopolyps basically represent these numerous bumps that arise on the surface of the colon
as a response to the healing of the ulceration.
So, after you get the ulceration and then you get healing,
then you're going to get these little bumps throughout the surface of the colon,
and those are called pseudopolyps.
At the same time, there will be loss of hostra,
and I'll show you a picture of loss of the hostra, again, at the very end of this section.
Now, what are the complications?
Well, one of the complications is something called toxic megacolon.
This is where you get massive dilation of the colon,
and the patients start to appear toxic where they are febrile, et cetera.
Another complication, and of course, the complication, by the way, of toxic megacolon is risk of rupture.
Another complication, perhaps the most important, the highest yield as far as the complications are concerned,
is carcinoma.
Now, when patients have ulcerative colitis, the feared complication is that they're going to develop dysplasia,
and then after the dysplasia, they're going to get carcinoma.
Now, the risk of carcinoma is based on two major factors.
Number one, the extent of colonic involvement.
So, the more you involve the colon, the more likely you are to get cancer.
And number two, the duration of the disease.
So, it takes about 10 years of disease before you really begin to worry about cancer.
Now, again, this is super important because it affects the management of patients with ulcerative colitis.
So, patients with ulcerative colitis will actually undergo screening colonoscopy,
and the purpose of screening colonoscopy in their case is to discover dysplasia,
because if there was dysplasia, that would indicate that you're one step closer to carcinoma.
And so, what they'll do during the colonoscopy is they'll go in there and just take random biopsies
from areas of disease or normal, what looks normal, and then they'll submit that to the pathologist,
and the pathologist will assess for the presence or absence of dysplasia.
Now, again, it's important to note, and it's high yield for examination purposes,
that the risk is based on two things, the extent of the colonic involvement and the duration of the disease.
So, usually, you don't get dysplasia until about 10 years into the disease.
What are the associations?
There's a couple associations.
One is called primary sclerosing cholangitis.
I'm going to bury that away in the back of your mind, and we'll talk about it later in our lectures.
But one very important one that I won't get a chance to touch on later in another chapter will be the P. Anka.
So, the P. Anka can be positive in ulcerative colitis, and actually, this is high yield for examination purposes.
Now, when you think about the P. Anka, what I'd like to remind you of is that the P. Anka can also be positive in a couple of vasculitities.
For example, when you think about P. Anka, you think about microscopic polyangiitis, you think about Church-Strauss,
and then you should also think about ulcerative colitis.
Again, that's important.
It's a little bit of a complicated discussion because this P. Anka is a little bit different than the P. Anka that you would have seen in the vasculitis,
but it is important to note that these patients can have a P. Anka.
And the final funny thing that likes to show up on exams is that smoking does protect against ulcerative colitis.
So, it's protective against ulcerative colitis.
Now, let's move to the opposite side of this chart and talk about Crohn's disease.
If ulcerative colitis is superficial involving the mucosa and the submucosa, then Crohn's disease is a full thickness inflammation.
And you get, instead of getting ulcers, you get these knife-like fissures.
So, what I mean by that is that if you're looking at the bowel wall, and, of course, you've got a mucosa and then a submucosa,
and then you've got a muscularis propria and a serosa, the way by which this disease sort of damages the wall
is that you get these large knife-like fissures of inflammation going through the entire thickness of the wall.
So, that's important to note.
Now, the location of Crohn's disease, if ulcerative colitis always starts at the rectum and then works its way back up to some part of the colon,
Crohn's disease can be anywhere from the mouth to the anus.
So, from the mouth all the way down to the anus.
And remember, if ulcerative colitis is a continuous lesion that starts at the rectum and works its way all the way up
and then is continuous around the entire tube, Crohn's disease can have skip lesions.
So, it can hit an area and then skip and then hit another area and then skip, and that's classic.
Now, the most common site of Crohn's disease is the terminal ileum, and the least common site is the rectum.
Most common site, terminal ileum.
Least common site, rectum.
So, because the terminal ileum is the most common site, these patients are going to present with right lower quadrant pain,
again, because the ileum is particularly involved, and they get non-bloody diarrhea, classically.
Now, when you think about what you would see histologically, remember that the hallmark of ulcerative colitis was crypt abscess.
Well, the hallmark of Crohn's disease is just going to be lymphocytes with granulomas.
Granulomas is really important.
So, you can see granulomas in Crohn's disease, and that's high yield.
Now, on gross exam, wherever there was damage, you would see cobblestoning of the mucosa,
and cobblestoning of the mucosa, again, represents the healing process,
and I'll show you a picture of that, as that's a very classic finding.
At the same time, you get creeping fat and stricture.
So, let me explain this.
Remember that in Crohn's disease, what you're going to get is you're going to get mucosa,
and then submucosa, and then muscularis propria, and then serosa,
and you're getting a full thickness inflammation through that entire wall.
Now, remember that outside of the serosa, you've got the mesentery hanging here,
and then you've also got adipose tissue along that mesentery.
So, imagine if you've got a full thickness inflammation,
then the next thing that's going to happen is you're going to get healing.
And when you get healing, you're going to get granulation tissue,
because you've knocked out the stem cells, and you're going to get fibrosis.
So, when you get granulation tissue and fibrosis, a couple things are going to happen,
but most importantly, you're going to have cells in here called the myofibroblasts.
Remember that the myofibroblasts are part of granulation tissue,
and they have contractile function.
So, that contractile function will actually cause this wall to contract and become fibrotic.
So, there'll be two consequences.
Number one, as you create this dense fibrosis along the wall,
you're going to narrow the lumen, creating what is called a stricture.
And so, you can actually sharply reduce the caliber of the lumen of this wall.
And number two, as the myofibroblasts are pulling up,
they're also going to pull the fat up with it.
And so, when you pull the fat up, the fat's going to then creep along the wall.
It's going to come closer in to the serosa, and they call that creeping fat.
So, that's what I mean here in your chart when I say that you get creeping fat and strictures.
Now, the strictures result in a classic sign called the string sign on imaging.
And again, I'll show you a picture of that at the very end.
As far as the complications of Crohn's disease are concerned,
the first one is malabsorption with nutritional deficiency.
And the idea here is that you have the potential to damage the small bowel.
The small bowel is essential for absorption.
And so, if there's significant damage to the small bowel,
you'll get malabsorption with nutritional deficiencies.
At the same time, these patients can develop calcium oxalate nephrolithiasis.
And the idea here is that normally you have oxalate in the gut.
However, we don't really absorb very much of that oxalate.
However, if there's inflammation of the bowel,
that then increases the ability of oxalate to come into the blood.
And if oxalate comes into the blood, it can eventually bind with calcium,
especially in the filtrate of the glomerulus, and then result in kidney stones.
And so, there's an increased risk of calcium oxalate nephrolithiasis,
and that is particularly high yield.
The patients can also form fistulas.
Fistulas are connections, abnormal connections between two tubes,
or abnormal connection between a tube and another surface.
So, that would be called a fistula.
And the idea here, again, is that, recall that you've got full thickness inflammation of the wall, correct?
So, when you have full thickness inflammation of the wall, you are weakening the wall.
Now, this wall could potentially rupture,
and imagine if this ruptures that the entire tube can then plug in to another tube.
And that would then be called a fistula.
So, that's important to understand in relatively high yield.
And then, there is a risk for carcinoma, but only if colonic disease is present.
And that's kind of based on the principles that we've already established for ulcerative colitis,
which is the fact that, when you think about the risk for cancer and ulcerative colitis,
remember that there's two factors.
Factor number one being the extent of colonic involvement.
And so, extent of colonic involvement is important.
And in this particular case, in Crohn's disease, if we have colonic involvement,
then there would be a risk for carcinoma.
And if there's no colonic involvement, then, of course, there would be a limited risk,
or almost no risk, for carcinoma.
Now, there are a bunch of associations with Crohn's disease.
They include ankylosing spondylitis, and we'll talk more about ankylosing spondylitis
when we do the musculoskeletal lecture.
Sacroiliitis, which you'll also hear about there.
You can get a migratory polyarthritis, where you get inflammation of joints,
and it involves multiple joints and can move from joint to joint to joint.
Erythema nodosum, which is a skin lesion, and uveitis, which would result in visual disturbances.
And so, these are some of the associations to merely be familiar with.
And the last point is that there's an increased risk for Crohn's disease in smokers.
So, with smoking, you protect against ulcerative colitis, but you increase the risk for Crohn's disease.
Now, what I'd like to do is show you a few pictures, and then we'll close off this section.
And so, the first picture here, this represents a patient with ulcerative colitis.
Now, the idea here is that this is the rectum, and what we're doing is you can see the redness represents the inflammation,
and you can see that you've also lost the folds as a result of that inflammation.
And you'll see this as we get closer to the normal mucosa.
So, here we are.
The way the ulcerative colitis works is that it always starts in the rectum, and then it works its way all the way up,
hitting the entire surface, until it eventually comes to a certain point where it stops.
So, here, it has stopped right here.
And then this represents normal.
All right?
And it, of course, starts in the rectum, works its way backward, paints the entire tube,
and then stops someplace in the colon.
The furthest it could go would be the cecum.
So, it's not allowed to go into the terminal ilium.
And this is, again, ulcerative colitis.
And the redness of the mucosa with the loss of the mucosal folds indicates that we've got ulcerative colitis as well.
Were you to look histologically, you would see the classic hallmark, which is a crypt abscess.
So, what I've illustrated here is that this circular space represents the crypt,
and within this crypt, you've got all of these neutrophils, which represents the crypt abscess.
When you get ulcerative colitis, you get loss of the holstra, which is these folds here,
all of these folds here in the wall, and that results in something called a lead pipe appearance.
So, here is all normal.
You can clearly see the holstra.
And here, you can see that you've lost them, and that's called a lead pipe appearance.
And I think this is a beautiful example of that.
Now, in the case of Crohn's disease, remember that you're going to get full thickness inflammation.
So, it's going to be full thickness from the top of the wall to the bottom of the wall.
And when you get full thickness inflammation, then the complication of that is that when you get healing,
you're going to get fibrosis of this entire thickness, and, of course, that is then going to narrow the lumen of the bowel.
And so, you can see here that this is normal, and all of a sudden, you've come into an area where this is narrow.
And that, again, is an example of a stricture.
Now, at the same time, this image is also highlighting the idea of cobblestoning,
so that when these patients get healing, the healing is represented by cobblestoning.
And so, you can clearly see it looks like a bunch of bricks laid down on the ground or on the street,
and that's the cobblestone appearance.
And at the same time, you can also notice here that some of the fat has been pulled up,
and so one of the features of Crohn's disease would also be creeping of the fat.
Now, if the patient presents with obstruction, you could do barium studies,
and in this particular case, you can see that this is the normal bowel here,
but when you come to this point of the bowel, the barium is barely passing through,
and that's because there's fibrosis here, and there's also fibrosis here.
Now, the inability to pass barium results in just this tiny wisp of barium coming through,
and that's called a string sign.
And that's the last image that highlights the important principles of both ulcerative colitis and Crohn's disease.
So, the next section will be our discussion of colon.